# **Billy Haile-Mariam**

# Senior Software Engineer

<u>belachewhm.github.io</u> <u>belachewhm@gmail.com</u>

# Summary

Senior Software Engineer with progressive development and leadership experience. Proven technical background that includes experience in Software Engineering, DevOps, Automation, Production Support, and Distributed Systems. Excels in fast-paced environments with demonstrated skills in leading team projects while ensuring optimal business operations.

#### **Technical Strengths**

Core Java Development Domain Driven Design Databases Web Development Event Driven Architecture Production Support Test Driven Development Test Driven Design Release Management RESTful Web Services Distributed Systems DevOps

# **Experience**

## **Greenwood Bank**

Senior Backend Engineer | Remote | May 2022 – June 2023

- Developed Kotlin Spring Boot microservices to run every part of the user onboarding and banking experience
- Integrated third party APIs with user onboarding flow for KYC checks using Spring Boot, Retrofit, and OKHttp
- Enhanced security for user login with two factor authentication
- Updated Postgres database schemas on an ongoing basis using Flyway migration scripts

## **United Services Automobile Association (USAA)**

Senior Software Engineer | Bank Deposits Technology | Plano, TX | February 2020 – May 2022

• Acted as the primary/lead developer on my team. Driving impactful and positive change throughout my organization. Responsible for code quality, future-proofing, and innovation

Technical Lead | Bank Deposits Technology | Plano, TX | October 2020 – February 2022

- Delivered a redesigned bank statement experience for all USAA member savings and checking accounts. Rearchitected major components of the original design to increase overall statement generation time and exceed
  performance requirements. Major technologies used include Java JBoss, Apache Kafka, Docker, Redhat
  OpenShift, IBM DB2, Linux, Splunk, Kibana, and Prometheus
- Worked with business partners to define, scope, and prioritize functional and non-functional feature requirements
- Performed code reviews, design sessions, and providing technical mentorship to team members

Software Engineer | Bank Deposits Technology | Plano, TX | April 2020 – October 2020

• Worked in a development team to redesign bank statements to a modern design, and to present all account information in a single consolidated view across web, mobile, and physical channels

Software Engineer | Production, Innovation, and Governance Services | Plano, TX | September 2019 – April 2020

Worked in a development team that was responsible for the creation and deployment of an internal tool that tracks
the migration status of service accounts as they move from a legacy system to Cyber Ark. Major technologies
used include: Angular 6, Java, Spring Boot, Gradle, Resilience4J, Docker, Kubernetes, Relational Databases
(MSSQL, DB2)

# **Capital One**

Software Engineer | Emerging Products | Seattle, WA | April 2018 – September 2019

- Worked on the back end of a distributed system that utilized technologies such as Java, Spring Boot, Axon/CQRS, Docker, Kafka, Hystrix, and AWS to build micro-services and RESTful APIs
- Worked closely with business partners to groom our project backlog, create stories, define acceptance criteria, demonstrate completed stories, and ensure that all stories meet our definition of done before being worked on
- Reviewed API documentation of a third-party vendor and built customer on-boarding/account funding features
- Used Hystrix to add retry logic to parts of our system that interact with external services
- Integrated our system with DynamoDB global tables to ensure no duplication of processed events, and also to ensure a seamless system transition from one region to another in a disaster/failover scenario
- Built custom swagger meta-annotations to increase code-reuse and standardize API documentation
- On-boarded teams of developers to the back end of the project by creating technical documentation and leading a workshop where we discussed all relevant information required to start contributing to the project

Software Engineer | Home Loans Servicing | Plano, TX | April 2017 – March 2018

- Designed and implemented a testing solution that involved wrapping a Spring Boot application around existing Selenium/Cucumber test automation and exposing it as a set of RESTful web services and a custom SwaggerUI interface. The application was then Dockerized, and deployed to AWS for start of day production validations, infrastructure rehydrations, and L3 production support application monitoring
- Refactored and added new features to an internal application that tracks the progress of home loans as they move from the originations to servicing department. Angular Front end with a Java/Spring Back end
- Automated a manual internal audit process using Java, Splunk, and SQL. Splunk logs from our online portal were
  cross-referenced with loan boarding data to validate that only customers who clicked an "I accept" button on our
  terms and conditions page were enrolled in recurring payments. A PDF report was then generated outlining every
  loan that either passed or failed the audit
- Resolved 234 production support tickets, including 212 customer digital escalations
- Built a Jira Dashboard using Jira queries and filters that tracked my team's progress on resolving customer digital escalations. This was extremely effective in helping us stay on top of incoming issues, and helped us reduce our ticket backlog in a timely and efficient manner
- Migrated Jenkins build jobs from an on-prem Jenkins 1.x instance to a Jenkins 2.x instance running on AWS
- Utilized GitHub, Jenkins, and cURL to automate part of our QA and Production deployments to AWS

## **Fidelity Investments**

Software Engineer | Pricing and Cash Management Services | Westlake, TX | January 2017 – March 2017

- Reverse engineered a Java web application from a WAR file (created through an Ant build) iinto a multi-module Maven project, while simultaneously migrating the application from Subversion to Git. This shrunk the size of the code base down from over 4 GB to approximately 45 MB, and improved the speed and consistency of each build
- Wrote scripts to automatically download, install, and configure software on Windows machines
- Installed and configured Jenkins agents to run on virtual machines
- Created a Maven parent project that defined clear and specific build goals for compilation, testing, packaging, installation, deployment, and reporting

Associate Software Engineer | Pricing and Cash Management Services | Westlake, TX | January 2016 – January 2017

- Developed a migration strategy to move development teams and their code repositories from Subversion to Git
- Facilitated training sessions to teach source control concepts using Git, Stash, SourceTree, and different development workflows (Central Repository, Feature Branches, Gitflow)
- Onboarded new and existing applications to CI/CD Jenkins pipelines, and modified existing pipelines as needed

Associate Software Engineer | Leap Program | Cary, NC | August 2015 – December 2015

- Completed training modules on Object-Oriented Analysis & Design, UNIX Essentials, Oracle 11g & Data Modeling, Big Data, Java/XML, The Spring Framework, Service Oriented Architecture, Dynamic Web Applications, and C#
- Developed a system for Fidelity's Asset Management division to import, normalize, and store data from credit rating agencies into Hadoop. This allowed the firm to find credit rating mismatches between that information and data imported from credit rating aggregation services, saving the company millions of dollars in liabilities

Technical Intern | Pricing and Cash Management Services | Westlake, TX | June 2014 – August 2014

- Constructed a web dashboard to showcase project overviews and associated metrics
- Managed and updated an online catalog of the services created

#### Ayoka Systems

Web Application Developer Intern | Arlington, TX | June 2013 – May 2014

- Designed and built web applications using the Grails framework and MVC architecture
- Worked with customers to gather requirements and perform testing to verify that specifications were met

#### Education

## The University of Texas at Arlington

Bachelor of Science | Computer Engineering | Arlington, TX | August 2010 – May 2015

- Senior Design Project Leader, Team SmartGrass
- Founding Father of the Theta-Omega Chapter of the Kappa Sigma Fraternity